Guide to the James Baenen Native American Slides 1962-1979
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
James Baenen Native American Slides
1962-1979
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
PC 193
Baenen, James A., 1938-2017
0.5 Linear feet of shelf space 1 Box 1190 Items
Photographic slides depicting Native American life, some original and some reproductions of other materials. Of most interest are likely original archeological slides in the northwest and southwest series.
James “Jim” Anthony Baenen (July 2, 1938-Oct. 5, 2017) received a B.A. from the University of Idaho before getting an M.A. in Anthropology at Washington State University in 1965. His WSU thesis dealt with hunting and fishing rights of the Nez Perce Indians. Baenen became a professor of Anthropology at Seattle Central Community College.
The collections consists of slides of and relating to Native Americans. Included are personal slides as well as commercial slides; these were apparently used both in his own research and for instruction purposes. About half of the slides are labeled with additional information, often including sources (for the reproductions) or dates.
The slides are housed in slide sheets, each holding up to 20 slides, and each individual slide sheet came from a single source in the original organization (i.e. no slide sheets were combined in processing). Those original sources were combined and organized into several series which are organized alphabetically by geographic region, and then alphabetically by subject within those. The few non-geographic materials, as well as unidentified sets, are located at the end. Dates are given in the folder descriptions below only for original photographs, and only where they could be determined.
This collection is open and available for research use.
James Dunne purchased these slides at at Jim Baenen’s estate sale in Lynnwood, WA on June 13th, 2019. He donated this collection to the Washington State University Libraries’ Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections (MASC) on August 24th, 2020, where they were retained as UPC 20-02.
James Baenen Nez Perce Audio Recordings, 1963 (Cage 938)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Baenen, James A., 1938-2017 -- Archives.
Indians of North America -- Photographs
Native Americans; Photographs
- Series 1: Northwest
  - Ozette. From filmstrip., 57 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Plateau., 9 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Plateau archaeology. 1962, 1968., 42 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Skagit dig., 11 items (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - St. John. WSU mammoth dig. 1962., 10 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Swinomish fish trap. Snee-oosh Point. 1973., 102 items (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Swinomish. Lone Tree Point, 1973., 35 items (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Yakima. Appears to be from filmstrip: Indians of Eastern Washington Today, Part 1, by J.W. Thompson., 46 items (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series 2: Southwest
  - Cliff dwellings. 1972-1973., 140 items (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Navajo. 1972-1978., 119 items (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs by Adam Clark Vroman (reproductions from originals created 1895-1904)., 65 items (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Pueblo. 1972-1979., 107 items (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Taos. 1972-1974., 37 items (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series 3: Other regions
  - Eastern woodlands., 25 items (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "KOT 2." 1970. (Far northern; only label is "oogruk!" This might be related to Netsilik?), 25 items (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Nepal. 1977., 7 items (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Netsilik., 11 items (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Plains., 64 items (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series 4: Non-geographic sets
  - Native American art., 219 items (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Unlabeled sets., 59 items (Box 1, Folder 20)